Ed Summers

ehs@pobox.com / @edsu / 240-478-7086 304 Brewster Court, Silver Spring, MD 20901

I am a software developer with two decades of experience working at the intersection of libraries, archives and the World Wide Web. I'm interested in how the web operates as a sociotechnical system, with a particular eye to its evolving architecture and practices of curation and preservation.

Work History

Resarch Faculty

Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities College Park, Maryland August 2014 - Present

- Social media data collection, analysis and preservation
- Digital humanities research and development
- Web and cloud based infrastructure development and sustainability

Information Technology Specialist

Library of Congress Washington, DC March 2006 – August 2014

- Digital preservation and repository software design and development
- Lead Software Developer on the National Digital Newspaper Project
- Social media preservation
- Design and implementation of the Library of Congress Linked Data Service
- Standards work in the World Wide Web Consortium: SKOS and RDFa

Senior Software Engineer

Follett Corporation McHenry, Illinois. May 2002 – March 2006

- Design and construction of a distributed knowledge management application
- Requirements gathering and project planning
- Web Service design and implementation
- Metadata harvesting and analysis
- Automated testing.

Senior Software Engineer

Cheetahmail New York, New York January 2000 - June 2002

- Large scale data ingest and normalization systems for modeling demographic information
- REST Web Services for internal and external data use

Electronic Resources Librarian

Old Dominion University Norfolk, Virginia July 1998 - January 2000

- Automated metadata processing for the Virtual Library of Viginia: MARC, TEI and EAD
- Designing cataloging workflows for OCLC / OPAC integration
- Collection development in applied mathematics

Visiting Assistant Professor

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Urbana, Illinois August 1996 - July 1998

• Website design and implementation

- Collection development: social work, arms control.
- Reference desk supervisor

Selected Publications

Summers, E., Wickner, A. (2019). Archival Circulation on the Web: The Vine-Tweets Dataset. $Cultural\ Analytics$. https://culturalanalytics.org/2019/06/archival-circulation-on-the-web-the-vine-tweets-dataset/

Proferes, N., Summers, E. (2019). Algorithms and Agenda-Setting in Wikileaks' #PodestaEmails Release. *Information, Communication & Society*. https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/1369118X.2019.1626469

Summers, E. (2018). Appraisal Practices in Web Archives. SocArXiv Papers. https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/75mjp

Ray, R., Brown, M., Fraistat, N., and Summers, E. (2017). Ferguson and the death of Michael Brown on Twitter: #blacklivesmatter, #tcot, and the evolution of collective identities. *Ethnic and Racial Studies*, 40(10). https://doi.org/10.1080/01419870.2017.1335422

Brown, M., Ray, R., Summers, E., and Fraistat, N. (2017). #sayhername: a case study of intersectional social media activism. $Ethnic\ and\ Racial\ Studies,\ 40(10),\ pages\ 1831-1846.$ https://doi.org/10.1080/01419870.2017.1334934

Summers, E. and Punzalan, R. (2017). Bots, seeds and people: Web archives as infrastructure. In *Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing, CSCW '17*, pages 821–834. https://arxiv.org/abs/1611.02493

Summers, E. (2015) Automating transparency: How I made congressed ts. Source. https://source.opennews.org/articles/automating.

Steiner, T., Van Hooland, S., and Summers, E. (2013). MJ no more: using concurrent Wikipedia edit spikes with social network plausibility checks for breaking news detection. In *Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on World Wide Web*, pages 791–794. International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee. https://arxiv.org/pdf/1303.4702.pdf

Summers, E. and Salo, D. (2013). Linking things on the web: A pragmatic examination of linked data for libraries, archives and museums. arXiv. https://arxiv.org/abs/1302.4591

Baker, T., Bechhofer, S., Isaac, A., Miles, A., Schreiber, G. and Summers, E. Key choices in the design of Simple Knowledge Organization System (SKOS). Journal of Web Semantics. https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1570826813000176

Summers, E., Isaac, A., Redding, C., and Krech, D. (2008). LCSH, SKOS and linked data. In *International Conference on Dublin Core and Metadata Applications 2008*, pages 25–33. http://dcpapers.dublincore.org/pubs/article/viewFile/916/912

Education

transparency/

PhD Information Studies

University of Maryland

2015 - Present

I am currently studying the activity of Web archiving, and Web archives as artifacts, through the lens of repair and sustainability studies.

M.S. Library Science

Rutgers University

1995 - 1996

My studies focused on the use of the emerging Web to deploy reference and cataloging services.

B.A. English and American Literature

Rutgers University

1987 - 1991

In my senior seminars I focused on the study of the African American experience through the works of James Baldwin. I minored in Computer Science.